[Music]
get I know it's late in the
evening my name is B Edwards and I'm the
executive director at the government
accountability project we're called Gap
um
[Applause]
we are um a law firm and an NGO and we
have spent about 35 years protecting and
defending whistleblowers in the United
States and increasingly
abroad
um we're here tonight of course to honor
John kiraku who is a gap client and a
whistleblower
um and we're very pleased to have Robert
chevrol here for this event and and we
wanted to welcome you um Gap is
um is in the business of protecting and
defending whistleblowers and um I wanted
to say a few words about the work that
we do before we proceed with the with
the um
program we work in a multifaceted way
with whistleblowers because as I'm sure
many of you know it is a very difficult
task to defend a whistleblower in court
the uh judicial system is not friendly
to whistleblowers in this country or in
many other countries so but we do
provide legal counsel to whistleblowers
who find themselves in the crosshairs of
their employers because they have
exposed corruption fraud abuse of
authority waste
misconduct and this does happen um
frequently and we think it's
increasingly
important uh as the United States has
deregulated sector after sector leaving
single individual whistleblowers as kind
of the last gasp of the public interest
um the voice of the public um in
corporations in government
and in intergovernmental
organizations we also work uh with the
Congress and governmental agencies
trying to strengthen whistleblower
legislation as many of you know in
November President Obama signed the
Whistleblower protection enhancement act
which was the culmination of a 133-year
campaign to strengthen whistleblower
protections uh at the federal level
because Court decisions over time time
had systematically weakened the
protections that were afforded by the wi
of blower protection act passed in 1989
so this was a tremendous Victory um last
year uh we also work with government
agencies to make sure that the laws are
enforced this is increasingly difficult
as many of you know and we work with the
media to call attention to uh the
disclosures that our whistleblower
clients make these disclosures are are
uh as you'll hear tonight fundamental to
the public interest um in this country
and we also uh organized public
education campaigns to try to affect the
change that would address the problems
that whistleblowers bring to to life
um we are here tonight to talk about
John kiraku in this particular case uh
John joh is the subject of a portrait
that has been painted by Robert shedly
part of a series of portraits America of
Americans who tell the truth and John
had a
particularly important and significant
truth to tell to the American public uh
a few words about about him he is a
veteran of the Central Intelligence
Agency as most of you know if you
followed the case uh he organized the
team in Pakistan after
911 that captured Abu Zeda in
2002 uh allegedly one of the most
important Al-Qaeda leaders at the time
um at that point John was asked if he
would be willing to learn enhanced
interrogation techniques uh which of
course later came to be exposed as
torture and he refused to learn those
techniques some years later in 2007 he
was interviewed on ABC News and was
asked about the capture of Aluma what
happened to him after that and it was in
that interview that John revealed that
there was a torture program that was um
underway and had been executed for some
years after
911 that it was not the work of a few
Rogue agents here and there it was
policy in the United States it had a
system a manual a staff a budget um and
this was a shocking disclosure to make
for me I I came of age in the
Vietnam uh
era and I remember when Daniel ellsburg
uh released the Pentagon pap and what a
scandal it was when Americans realized
that there there we had been essentially
tricked into a war in uh in Southeast
Asia and for all of the repression and
the dishonesty of the government that
was revealed at that time I have to say
I never thought I would be living in a
country that would send a whistleblower
like John to jail and it's is truly a a
shocking development that um I think
really needs to be needs to be
remarked uh I wanted then to um go on
and introduce our our um National
Security and human rights program
director she will also speak about
John's case she is jine Rak I think um
many of you know know her she herself
was a whistleblower at the justice
department uh who revealed the unethical
treatment of a prisoner in the hands of
of US forces after Jess speaks uh
robertt chedle will also speak about uh
the portrait series and we'll have the
unveiling of the portrait and then we
will hear from the man of the hour John
kir so Jess
[Applause]
um well
it's really difficult to be here under
these
circumstances it's an absolute travesty
of justice that the only person who will
go to jail
in connection with the bush era torture
program is the person who blew the
whistle on
torture John kiraku refused to
participate in
torture at a time when government
officials were still claiming torture
was a work of a few bad apples John
helped Expos the truth that torture was
a program approved at the highest levels
of government he even had the audacity
to say that water boarding is torture a
conclusion with which our attorney
general
agrees John's guilty plea represents a
tragic bookend to the torture narrative
a sad and shameful chapter in our
country's
history I have always said that truth is
not a partis is an issue
unfortunately however the responsibility
for torture and lack of accountability
also lies squarely with both
parties the Bush Administration ushered
in an era of expanded executive power at
the expense of individual
liberties Bush orchestrated a policy of
extraordinary rendition indefinite
detention and torture
the Obama Administration has failed to
successfully roll back much of that
executive power and has even expanded it
to include assassination without due
process and criminal prosecution of
whistleblowers who expose fraud waste
abuse and
illegality the Obama Administration also
holds responsibility for failing to hold
accountable
anyone anyone for the torture program
including the lawyers who wrote the
legal memoranda authorizing torture the
officers who ordered torture the agents
who carried it out and the operatives
who destroyed the videotapes of it one
of whom Jose Rodriguez who personally
ordered the destruction of the
videotapes and is enjoying a book tour
right
now now The Whistleblower John is the
only one going to
jail using the criminal justice system
and the Draconian heavy-handed out of
scope Espionage Act in particular as a
tool for whistleblower
retaliation and silencing dissent
undermines not only
the criminal justice system but
democracy as a whole the Espionage Act
is meant to go after spies not
whistleblowers Rob shedly an amazing
artist deserves enormous credit for
seeing through the government's
distorted picture of John kiraku and so
many others and for recognizing John for
what he is whistleblower and Truth
teller who showed enormous Civic courage
and standing up against an exposing one
of the darkest chapters in US
history I had the fortune of meeting Rob
when he painted my portrait for a
brainchild of his an exhibit called
Americans who tell the truth I was
astounded by the people with whom I I
was honored to be pictured beneath each
picture there's a quote from something
each individual has said and it's an
amazing series that's been traveling in
exhibit around the country um and there
was an initial printing of the book of
the first portraits um the good thing is
there are a lot of Truth tellers in
America a lot of amazing people who are
doing amazing things unfortunately we're
still very isolated one from another
often because of vindictive criminal
prosecutions where we're tagged as
traitors turn coats denters enemies of
the state and that alienates us from our
natural allies in the open government
Community good government groups civil
liberties groups and whistleblower
organizations Rob thankfully has been
able to bring us under one umbrella the
truth and for that I am eternally
grateful as are the many other people
whose portraits I know he has drawn um
I'm truly grateful Rob and you can tell
us more about your project and thank you
from the bottom of my heart
[Applause]
closer closer to the
mic it's a sound man I know that guy
thank you jeline that
was that was a movie I and I want to
thank gap for arranging and making this
possible but of course what I really
want to thank is
John I'm a I'm a pter um you're a
courageous Citizen and I think it's
extraordinary what you've done and it's
also an extraordinary price you're
paying and so anything we can
do um to bring attention to what's
happening here and to try
to make some justice out of this moment
in which the law is being used to
subvert Justice um will be the benefit
of all of us I wanted to say a couple of
words about the American to tell the
truth project it's it's something I I um
never expected to be doing and also
didn't want to do exactly 11 years ago
this month I was a surrealist who was
supporting a family making a very
different kind of paintings but as be
suggested earlier you know we were
being um led into another War
by a an Administration that was using
fear and
propaganda and
racism and fundamentalism to engineer
and manipulate the American people into
accepting an illegal and immoral War and
the media was not doing anything really
uh except you know sort of the
alternative media to tell the real story
that they should be doing in a
democracy I live in a little town on the
coast of Main and and I was thinking you
know what in the world can I do at this
moment to get a voice one consideration
was just to leave the country I felt so
ashamed of what this country was doing
and its arrogance but I didn't really
want to do that I think I've got to to
fight what's going on and find some way
to feel less alienated from my own
country and it uh you know the first
feelings I had were well I you know was
what to do with all this anger and grief
and you know most of us know that if
that's what you throw at people uh they
don't really want to see it and so the
question became what to do and uh I
finally came out of sort of a sense of
Shame and thought well if I
could instead of U obsessing about the
people who are lying start surrounding
myself with the people that I admire
from the country you know basically I
will feel a lot better and Where it All
Began I thought instead of thinking all
the time about Dick chain why don't I
think about W Whitman and fr Douglas and
Susan thean Elizabeth ktie St Alice Paul
L Bar people Howard Zim you know why
don't I just spend my time thinking
about the people that I love who to me
Define the best of this country and
that's where this project began began
with an idea to paint 50 portraits I
never painted a portrait and to into
these portraits words of those people
and then use them hopefully to present
to other people about actually what is
the most noble thing about this country
is the way individuals and organizations
have fought to close the gap between
what we say we are and what we actually
do and to me that's where our real
history is and the most important part
of it but I want to say something about
uh
about John and how he fits into
this my view
of this history and and all these people
like jesselyn like Tom Drake like
hellberg like so many others who have
tried to make this country more honest
and it comes from you know just a couple
days ago was U our Martin Luther King
holiday and there's a a phrase he used
in I Have a Dream speech the one that uh
it's a phrase that is not talked about
much but to me is one of the most
defining of that speech in a peculiar
way and I'll explain what I mean in the
very first part of the speech he talks a
little bit about the coming to to
Washington to black people you know to
cash a check that had been long
uncashable and then he defines the
American dream as the riches of freedom
and the security of Justice you know he
doesn't Define it in terms of material
wealth or you know upward Mobility or
you know just being able to do anything
you want to do the riches of freedom and
the security and
Justice and I was looking at that phrase
one day and I thought where where are we
really with that and if you
invert both those phrases you become a
lot closer to where we really
are the freedom of
riches and the justice of
security you know when you're so
entitled that you think you have the
freedom to take riches for yourselves
and from the rest of the
world that's basically the excuse for
imperialism and when you think that your
Justice is derived from your security
rather than your your security derived
from
Justice then you get torture then you
get unwed surveillance then you get
preemptive Wars then you get all kinds
of secrecy you get the National Security
State and you get the necessity of
someone like John who has to finally you
know stand up and say I won't do this
you can't do this somebody has to say no
and I think it's incredibly important um
you know it's it's a such a shame that
the Integrity of the country often rests
on single single individuals around
issues like this to do the right thing
and then pay the enormous price for it
and so all of us you know have to be
incredibly
grateful um maryan Driscoll who about
after John speaks he going to sing um
and I I just want to say a word about
her because about a year ago she got in
touch with me I didn't know her she's
this amazing jazz pianist who said she'd
like to make a new American song book
based on the quotes on the on the pits
that I painted and we have now been for
the last year working together it's
extraordinary um on the way down we were
talking
about a lot about John and about his
quote and I'm not going to read the
quotes I actually want John to read it
when we unveil the portrait but I just
wanted to read the the first line of it
and probably a lot of you know this but
it starts out even if torture works it
canot be
tolerated and I think a lot of people
would look at that statement and they
say wait a minute we all know torture
doesn't
work why would you even say
that it's very important to say that
it's very important to say you know it's
it's like you know um you know if you
had a u a car without an engine in it
and said you know this this thing is
working so I we can't drive
anyway but if you have a car with a
really good engine in it and then say
it's wrong to drive that car the only
right thing to do is walk that's a whole
different thing and to say you know even
if torture works it's something
that so defines our
species as something we don't want to
be uh that it's cannot be
tolerated and so to me that just to say
that you know that way you know because
the excuse for it for years has been
well it works and uh we need it and then
if you think of if our Justice is
derived from security then it's okay you
know that
justifies anyway I'm going to unbre this
and John want you come up there and
maybe help me do that and then read the
quote on it and then
[Applause]
w
see if I can see this I got new classes
last
week even if torture works it cannot be
tolerated not in one case or a thousand
or a million if their efficacy becomes
the measure of abor Acts all sorts of
unspeakable crimes somehow become
acceptable I may have found myself on
the wrong side of the government on
torture but I'm on the right side of
history there are things we should not
do even in the name of National Security
one of them I now firmly believe is
torture
[Applause]
as um I know Jess or B said these
portraits are now 187 of them my goal
was 50 and I have not been able to stop
and I have no intention of stopping it's
just too amazing what I'm learning the
people I'm learning about and the
history I'm learning about and we're
also Americans to tell the truth is now
working with Deborah merer and teaching
for Change and the zad project and
rethinking schools um the they travel to
schools colleges museums libraries
community centers all over the United
States and you know having John's
portrait in this collection is now going
to be able to in a sense use him no
matter where he is where they put it you
know we're going to be able to use him
to teach these values
to American citizens everywhere
[Applause]
than please uh thanks please forgive the
use of prepared
remarks but uh I have to pass everything
through my attorneys they say I have a
tendency to slander
people which I admit I do so I'm going
to try to stick by these so first of all
my first three paragraphs were
introducing myself you know who I am and
then I go on to say I won't revisit the
details of my case I've already angered
the judge enough in that respect
um so first I want to thank Rob shedly
this is just so overwhelming and so
humbling I I can't believe I'm standing
here looking at something like this it's
just incredible thank you very much
where did he go there he is Rob thank
you I don't even have words to thank you
for something like this something that
I'm very proud of and I I think my kids
are just going to love I'm going to
start by saying that I accept my
sentence of 30 years in prison 30 oh my
God 30 months in
prison
ohy it was the 30 years I was trying not
to get 30 months in prison without
bitterness and I mean that I accept it
without bitterness I'm sorry for the
pain that I've caused my family which
has been
considerable U but I believe that when
people see something that's wrong and
cruel and unjust and undemocratic that
they have to step up and say something
about it I'm not naive I know that
National Security and intelligence and
counterterrorism is a very tough Arena I
knew that there was a a risk to what I
was
doing but I also know that debasing
another person and serializing human
rights abuses under legal paper is not
the American way and it's not something
that as Americans we should be engaged
in it's not what our democracy stands
for and I didn't want any part of it I
still
don't in December of 2007 I said on ABC
News that we should not be torturing
because America is better than that
Americans are more principled we're more
honorable we're more Humane and we are
more responsible we are not a lowest
common denominator country measuring
what is right by what others do and the
American way stands for something and it
is not
torture so I head to prison accepting
responsibility for my actions and hoping
that maybe the country is better and
more informed and more transparent for
the debate that I helped to initiate
I've never gained anything for what I've
said publicly in fact I've lost
everything and I believe I was
prosecuted not for what I did but for
who I am a c I
officer who said torture was wrong and
ineffective and went against the
grain if I'm actually guilty of a crime
then I should uh have a lot of company
in prison a long list of people whose
books and articles and TV interviews and
sexual Dianes have compromised National
Security and violated the country's
secrecy but that's a different
issue um I will be able to tell my
children that they Dad paid his debt to
society in the hope that just maybe
Society comes out the better for it the
irony as just R pointed out a few
minutes ago is that I never tortured
anybody uh but I'm heading to prison
while the torturers and the lawyers who
papered over it and the people who
deceived it and the man who destroyed
the proof of it the tapes will never
face Justice and that's the saddest part
of this
story there are many people I'd like to
thank people who have stuck by me
through this nightmare and who have been
generous with their time time friendship
and in many cases their money first
again to Rob
shedly it's just so it's just so
overwhelming Rob I I don't know what to
say other than I absolutely love it and
I'm I'm humbled that you would have even
thought to choose me for this
series thanks also to bus boys and Poets
terrific venue and to the zened
foundation or zened project rather for
tonight's event thank you very very much
to Jess Rak to Kathleen mlen and to the
government accountability project J R
seriously JN R is the first person that
I spoke
to that is we jine is the first person I
spoke to after my arrest I didn't know
where to turn and a friend of mine
texted me uh with a link to an article
that jeline was quoted in and he said
you have to get in touch with this woman
and that was the smartest thing that
I've done in the past
year I want to thank also um two legal
advisers who have become friends Bruce
Fine who is one of the most honorable
and one of the most brilliant
constitutional attorneys in our country
and John ker I have a
large I have a large legal team as you
might
expect so a very quick thank you to
Plato cacheris Bob Trout John Hundley
Jesse winterr Mark mcdal Jim Sher and
Karen
Williams
[Applause]
uh I also want to thank
somebody who's become a dear friend in
this whole in this whole mess and that's
Tom
Drake Tom Drake is a real
hero Tom was the first person to be
charged with Espionage by the Obama
Administration multiple counts of
Espionage of course he had never
committed Espionage they just didn't
like what he had to say and in fact what
he had to say was unclassified but they
charged him with Espionage he faced
something like 35 years in prison and
and he remained steadfast and tough to
the point where the entire case
collapsed around him and he walked away
a free man the reason why Tom is so
heroic to me is that he didn't have the
support network that I have there was no
Tom Drake to help Tom Drake like there
is Tom Drake helping me and so I have
nothing but admiration for him he's he's
been a very good and true friend
uh Alex georgiadis who's here tonight uh
Gus Moses Rich Klein Bruth Bruce and
Elizabeth ryell former CIA uh colleagues
of mine Chuck Murphy Don Roberts Tom and
Julia Fitzpatrick John Spano mik signatu
Jim spon and my cousin Kip ree who's
here as well and runs a Blog that's been
completely supportive of me thank you
also to Ralph nater and the nater Family
Foundation Ralph nater has been
steadfast in his support of me I was
thrilled just to be in the same room
with Ralph nater and get my picture
taken with him and here I get phone
calls now telling me all the things
Ralph nater is doing for me it's it's
really
humbling um I'd like to thank Liberty
University this is Jerry falwell's
University when I was arrested Liberty
University offered me work because
torture is not
Christian and as much an Odd Couple as
we may be they have been steadfast in
their support
and so I want to thank them
publicly um the Greek American Community
has come out very strongly for me too
and I wanted to thank the brothers of
the helenic American uh Leadership
Council and the uh American helenic
educational and Progressive Association
and
finally they've been really
great but the greatest the greatest
person has been my wife Heather who
unfortunately has the flu tonight and
can't can't be here but um Heather
Heather lost her job at the CIA just
because she's married to me she was a
she was a senior Cia officer and really
one of the best analysts in the entire
uh intelligence Community but she she
had to leave that job just simply
because she's married to me um I'm sorry
about that I will say that our lives are
better now that neither one of us is
connected to the CIA but
uh but that was really the wrong thing
for them to do and I that ever since it
happened with that said Heather has been
completely Rock Solid in support of me
and I couldn't possibly have gotten
through this without her so thanks to
them thanks to all of you for being here
and thanks to Rob shev for this
beautiful for
[Applause]
thank you John I want to make a little
commercial plea and that is that John's
terrific book The Reluctant
spy is on sale out here um also the
American to tell the truth book of the
first 50 portraits is also here
and
posters of the portrait uh are also here
the proceeds from these will benefit
teaching for change Americans to tell
the truth and John's defense fund so if
you if some you're interested in the
poster and I hope some of you might be
we would both love to sign it thank you
very much and now um Mar and Drisco is
going to sing John's uh quote
[Applause]
first off I guess I can say thank you
for here very I'm honored to be
here
for for
[Music]
even if T you was
it
canot
[Music]
beated a million
see becomes the
meure of
[Music]
a all of
unspeakable
[Music]
crimes
somehow become
[Music]
on the right side
of my
[Music]
May on the side
even if torture
works it cannot be
[Music]
not in
one for
[Music]
[Applause]
it I just wanted to make sure we
dedicated ourselves to the importance of
John's work this evening and
concentrated on his words and also he
did tell me that his favorite musician
is Pete
Seager and in light of that and now
having had the opportunity to meet John
I am going to write a to about John in
i' to leave
[Music]
you T
[Applause]
so thank you to
Maran to jeline and to John and to
Robert I did want to say one practical
thing as you might imagine the events of
the last few years have been financially
ruinous for John and his
family and to help his family while he
Ison Gap is setting up a special fund
you can make a tax exempt a tax
deductible contribution to Gap indicate
that it's for the John Kaku fund and we
will make sure that it goes to the
support of his family while he's in jail
um we'll be hanging around here for a
short while if you want to talk to any
and all of us about whistleblowers we're
here in the room until
I think also again's books are sale
in thank you very very much for coming
andk
[Applause]
really good now it's perfect great
shoulder
go
hey how are you good to meet you in
person thanks for
yeah we
[Music]
got's Hi how are you hey great yeah
terrif thanks
allk
[Music]
guys iate thank you very much
very